<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>momeng</title><link href="http://jimperio.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://jimperio.com/feeds/jomel-imperio.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://jimperio.com/</id><updated>2015-05-13T00:00:00+08:00</updated><entry><title>Housekeeping</title><link href="http://jimperio.com/housekeeping.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-05-13T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Jomel Imperio</name></author><id>tag:jimperio.com,2015-05-13:housekeeping.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's again been too long since I've updated here, but late is better than never! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've recently been more consciously working on my software development skills and portfolio (probably the subject of another entry entirely), so I revisited this blog and cleaned up and updated the backend a little.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's see how I've fared on the goals in &lt;a href="http://jimperio.com/hello-again-world.html"&gt;my last post&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning to drive - No progress. License is still expired and missing, and I still need to get more informal practice before applying for a license (and taking the exam) again.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Side projects - I haven't started any new ones, and I've more or less gotten bored with the Phaser game. I might pick that up again, but I'm now leaning towards starting a project in Python instead!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning a new programming language - Haskell has been fun and I'm continuing to work on exercises, putting up my answers &lt;a href="https://github.com/jimperio/haskell-exercises"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. I'm also considering starting a small project in C.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learning to swim - Sadly, we've moved out of White Plains and no longer have easy access to a swimming pool.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write and blog regularly - heh.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It pays to keep in mind: just keep moving forward!&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Hello (again), world</title><link href="http://jimperio.com/hello-again-world.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-01-28T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Jomel Imperio</name></author><id>tag:jimperio.com,2015-01-28:hello-again-world.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am severely out of blogging shape, but the first step is always the hardest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hello, 2015, let's kick ass! It's time to finally do the things I've wanted to do for so long:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn to drive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work on side-projects (a toy project using Phaser is up at GitHub: &lt;a href="http://jimperio.github.io/speedy-spin"&gt;game&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://github.com/jimperio/speedy-spin"&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn a new (programming) language (giving &lt;a href="http://learnyouahaskell.com/"&gt;Learn You a Haskell&lt;/a&gt; another try)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn to swim&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write and blog regularly&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I need to remember: it's just about continuing to move forward, bit by bit, every day!&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Island Vacation</title><link href="http://jimperio.com/island-vacation.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-09-27T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Jomel Imperio</name></author><id>tag:jimperio.com,2013-09-27:island-vacation.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Part 1 (2012)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It rained again today.&lt;br /&gt;
Sand's less white than beige&lt;br /&gt;
and not quite fine&lt;br /&gt;
but still I felt the quivering&lt;br /&gt;
of the spaces between my fingers.&lt;br /&gt;
I walked as slowly as memory-&lt;br /&gt;
you and me once did&lt;br /&gt;
on that rainy beach more beautiful than this.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now it's too quiet.&lt;br /&gt;
Across this ocean pretending to be a lake&lt;br /&gt;
another island where you are not&lt;br /&gt;
unrolls along the horizon.&lt;br /&gt;
Glassy gray reflects bright blue.&lt;br /&gt;
Fellow travelers slice dark lines across the water&lt;br /&gt;
that, like them, disappear.&lt;br /&gt;
And what about these, my lines for you?  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What about the curve of you&lt;br /&gt;
once right next to, once touching me?&lt;br /&gt;
Just another skein of rain from sky to sea?&lt;br /&gt;
What of our once-parallel trajectories,&lt;br /&gt;
the sharing of presents and histories&lt;br /&gt;
in effortless communion?&lt;br /&gt;
The same saltwater may lap at all beaches&lt;br /&gt;
but will our footsteps again follow the same shore?  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's another dispatch from where I am&lt;br /&gt;
to where you are. When you open this,&lt;br /&gt;
remember my lips against your forehead.&lt;br /&gt;
Remember the nearness of my smile&lt;br /&gt;
and the soft clarity of my voice beside your ear&lt;br /&gt;
and know that I think of you always.&lt;br /&gt;
Know that though my lines may sometimes bend&lt;br /&gt;
they always - will always - reach for you.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part 2 (2013)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here where they drive on the wrong side&lt;br /&gt;
with their rented motorbikes&lt;br /&gt;
I pedal myself to and fro.&lt;br /&gt;
Here where we all walk like intruders,&lt;br /&gt;
dress with fashionable disregard,&lt;br /&gt;
and dance until moonset&lt;br /&gt;
as if trying to close the gap&lt;br /&gt;
between ourselves and ourselves.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here where the food is fresh and sweet and spicy.&lt;br /&gt;
Here where the rain never lasts for long.&lt;br /&gt;
Here where good cheer seems mandatory.&lt;br /&gt;
Here where the parties last forever.&lt;br /&gt;
Here where perception is easy to alter,&lt;br /&gt;
memory easier to lose,&lt;br /&gt;
and easiest of all to fall&lt;br /&gt;
into the unbroken horizon.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here where like locusts in a frenzy&lt;br /&gt;
they swarm and use themselves up&lt;br /&gt;
leaving behind only silent husks,&lt;br /&gt;
here where you touch each other briefly&lt;br /&gt;
and without care,&lt;br /&gt;
here where we are all far from where we should be.&lt;br /&gt;
Here where none of this even matters;&lt;br /&gt;
not until it's time to go back home.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here where barely anyone speaks my language&lt;br /&gt;
I came to find my voice,&lt;br /&gt;
but the quietness of the day defeats me&lt;br /&gt;
so I sit and let the sound engulf me&lt;br /&gt;
and a stillness hold me in place.&lt;br /&gt;
Here where they come to lose themselves&lt;br /&gt;
I came not to find myself, exactly,&lt;br /&gt;
but just what holds everything together.  &lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>The secret to writing poetry</title><link href="http://jimperio.com/the-secret-to-writing-poetry.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-04-19T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Jomel Imperio</name></author><id>tag:jimperio.com,2013-04-19:the-secret-to-writing-poetry.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I just finished Nicholson Baker's &lt;em&gt;The Anthologist&lt;/em&gt;. It was a fairly quick read, in Baker's smart, introspective, stream-of-consciousness style, filled with well-observed detail and unabashed(ly interesting) digressions. There are funny moments, beautiful ones, poignant ones, and all throughout a comfortable verisimilitude. It seemed to me an honest and convincing portrayal of what might be going through a poet's mind and how they look at the world and think about poetry. The protagonist also makes a pretty good case for rhyme and meter, and makes me realize that I do need to give those more attention and study if I'm serious about continuing to attempt to write poetry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking to class of poets, he manages to summon up a wonderful piece of advice, which I think deserves thinking about. In response to the question, and I paraphrase, how do you begin writing a poem?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I said, "Well, I'll tell you how. I ask a simple question. I ask myself: What was the very best moment of your day?" The wonder of it was, I told them, that this one question could lift out from my life exactly what I will want to write a poem about. Something that I hadn't known was important will leap up and hover there in front of me, saying I am&amp;mdash;I am the best moment of the day.... Often, I went on, it's a moment when you're waiting for someone, or you're driving somewhere, or maybe you're just walking diagonally across a parking lot and you're admiring the oil stains and the dribbled tar patterns. One time it was when I was driving past a certain house that was screaming with sun-litness on its white clapboards, and then I plunged through tree shadows that splashed and splayed over the windshield. I thought, Ah, of course&amp;mdash;I'd forgotten. You, windshield shadows, you are the best moment of the day. "And that's my secret, such as it is," I said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Rationale</title><link href="http://jimperio.com/rationale.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-04-18T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Jomel Imperio</name></author><id>tag:jimperio.com,2013-04-18:rationale.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;You know you're a rusty blogger when the old doubts regain their power to reduce you to feeling like a worthless, self-indulgent git with nothing to say and no right to erect and stand on yet another tiny cyberspace platform. I know that it's already (mostly) socially-acceptable for anyone to start a blog and just begin running off at the fingers, and yet, don't we all aspire to actually live up to our above-average perception of ourselves?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And all that is perhaps just a very long-winded (and, yes, self-indulgent) way of saying that in this essay I simply aim to justify blogging to myself. Let's begin with the easy, obvious reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;A software developer should really have a website.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even just a bare-bones one such as this. I can't believe I haven't gotten around to doing this until just now. It's fun as a little side project, especially since I'm not currently doing web development. I'll get to mess around with and learn about a different set of tools for a different problem domain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;It's a great way to get oneself to write, and to hone those writing skills.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, obviously. I suppose the term "blogging" could be stretched to cover certain cases that involve little to no actual writing at all, but those cases aren't what I want to do or talk about here!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting a blog more or less also means committing to updating that blog with content regularly. I recently again came across Ira Glass' wonderful articulation of the need to just keep producing work, if you're really serious about getting better at what you do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What nobody tells people who are beginners — and I really wish someone had told this to me . . . is that all of us who do creative work, we get into it because we have good taste. But there is this gap. For the first couple years you make stuff, and it’s just not that good. It’s trying to be good, it has potential, but it’s not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But your taste, the thing that got you into the game, is still killer. And your taste is why your work disappoints you. A lot of people never get past this phase. They quit. Most people I know who do interesting, creative work went through years of this. We know our work doesn’t have this special thing that we want it to have. We all go through this. And if you are just starting out or you are still in this phase, you gotta know it’s normal and the most important thing you can do is do a lot of work. Put yourself on a deadline so that every week you will finish one story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is only by going through a volume of work that you will close that gap, and your work will be as good as your ambitions. And I took longer to figure out how to do this than anyone I’ve ever met. It’s gonna take awhile. It’s normal to take awhile. You’ve just gotta fight your way through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BI23U7U2aUY"&gt;source video&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every writer has at some point had the sinking experience of reading someone else's work and thinking, that's it, there's no hope for me, there's no way I'll ever write anything nearly as good! Here, Glass reassures us: that experience is universal, and it can eventually be overcome, if you just put in the effort, pay your dues, and do your work. The quality of your work will eventually catch up to your taste. It seems so perfectly obvious, but if it were, then why do a lot of creatives still seem to have trouble accepting it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I know I still have a long way to go. And keeping a blog will help me force myself to just keep writing. Having my writing accessible online to the whole world will hopefully also help to rein in any indulgent tendencies and to keep me disciplined about always producing effective, interesting writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Writing things out aids in processing and understanding them.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In attempting to explain or express something to someone else, one of course has to do it to oneself first. And one can't write about anything without having to clarify it in one's mind first, think about it in an orderly way, and fit it into the rest of one's current overall mental model. To teach anything, one has to learn and understand it first. So I should expect that if I can just be disciplined about what I write, I will end up learning a lot and improving my understanding significantly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tried to start an "idea blog" before, where I was going to write about all the interesting things I end up reading and learning and studying about, but it sadly never really got off the ground. The concept is sound, I think, I just need to actually do it and write!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a more personal note, I'm one of those people who process life events rather slowly, and often it's only after I actively think about things by writing them out that I feel like I've actually thought about them properly. I've learned to recognize how journalling and attempting to express my thoughts help to stave off that numb feeling of just being mutely swept along.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1&gt;Lastly, who knows, maybe you, dear reader, might also get something from all this!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I put this at the very last because, truthfully, I don't really expect any significant readership. But still, with previous blogs, I did experience some few moments of connection with readers, and I'd feel really lucky if this blog enables those to happen again. It was extremely satisfying to know that what I wrote and put out there can actually have an effect on others. (I'm still inordinately proud of having convinced a stranger on the Internet who just happened upon my blog of the charms of Haruki Murakami...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Am I convinced? Well, let's just say that I'm getting there. The process of conceiving and writing this essay did help exactly as I described above, and I'm growing more excited about writing more in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let the positive feedback loop slowly begin!&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Anathem and the appeal of the academe</title><link href="http://jimperio.com/anathem-and-the-appeal-of-the-academe.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-04-15T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Jomel Imperio</name></author><id>tag:jimperio.com,2013-04-15:anathem-and-the-appeal-of-the-academe.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm currently reading -- well, devouring, really -- Neal Stephenson's &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anathem" title="Anathem on Wikipedia"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Anathem&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. I've previously read and thoroughly enjoyed his &lt;em&gt;Cryptonomicon&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Snow Crash&lt;/em&gt;, and I have to say that he writes refreshingly intellectual pageturners, which seems to me a fairly rare class. (Of course, I'd be really glad to be proved otherwise!) I mean, one wouldn't generally expect something like the many-worlds interpretation of quantum mechanics to be an important theme in a pageturner, or for the main character to be an academic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things that attracted and held me to &lt;em&gt;Anathem's&lt;/em&gt; world is the concept and depiction of the Mathic culture and society. In brief, it's a manifestation of the proverbial ivory tower. Members of this society, called avout, swear a vow to withdraw from the outside world and devote themselves to learning and the pursuit of knowledge. Their retreats (called maths) are essentially secular monasteries -- they don't abide by any particular religion, and most are in fact areligious. Maths are generally self-sufficient and self-contained, and the avout are provided rigorous intellectual training before being set free to pursue their interests, no matter how arcane or esoteric.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It all sounds so much like a place I would love to be able to call home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, I do realize that the whole thing is a big idealization. In the real world, entering the academe comes with its own particular set of practical difficulties. Still, for me it does express quite well the appeal of the academe: the freedom to learn for learning's sake, the heavy-if-not-exclusive dealing in intellectual abstractions and generalities, the thrill of doing research and discovering new things about the world or useful new ways of looking at the world, and the feeling of becoming part of a great tradition. There are the impassioned debates and disciplined conversations one can have with fellow academics. There is that purity and elegance of theory over practice that I still can't quite verbalize even though it's what supposedly made my naive pre-college self choose "pure" physics over applied physics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can't say whether I'll ever go back to university, but it probably will always remain in that "someday maybe" compartment in the back of my mind. In the meantime, I'll feed the urge with novels like &lt;em&gt;Anathem&lt;/em&gt; and my little hobbyist forays into writing, philosophy, history, and literature, which I really do need to make more time and find more energy for...&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Setting up a workflow</title><link href="http://jimperio.com/setting-up-a-workflow.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-04-12T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Jomel Imperio</name></author><id>tag:jimperio.com,2013-04-12:setting-up-a-workflow.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Slowly getting this blog up to speed. As mentioned previously, I'm currently hosting this website on &lt;a href="http://pages.github.com"&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;, and I've no real complaints so far. Setup has been mostly painless and easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I moved from a User page to a Project page, which has the benefit of allowing me to keep both the source and the actual static website output in the &lt;a href="http://github.com/jimperio/jimperio.blog"&gt;same repo&lt;/a&gt;, only on different branches. &lt;a href="https://github.com/davisp/ghp-import"&gt;ghp-import&lt;/a&gt; is very useful and makes managing the gh-pages branch almost brainless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully by next week I'll be able to focus more on writing new entries. Although I have to admit that this setup stuff is fun, too! I haven't used git much (at all) on previous projects, and it still feels a bit strange to me, being more used to hg. I'm also pretty new to Markdown, and I haven't really touched HTML/CSS in a long time...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I'm just glad it was this easy to get a(n admittedly simple, static) website up and running. Now, to optimize the writing, updating, and deployment workflow!&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>It's alive!</title><link href="http://jimperio.com/its-alive.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-04-11T00:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Jomel Imperio</name></author><id>tag:jimperio.com,2013-04-11:its-alive.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, that wasn't so hard. Pulled the trigger today on this jimperio.com domain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Currently using &lt;a href="http://github.com/getpelican/pelican"&gt;Pelican&lt;/a&gt;, and hosting the static output on &lt;a href="http://pages.github.com"&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;. The source for this blog is also on &lt;a href="https://github.com/jimperio/jimperio.blog"&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We'll see what we can make of this. Quite obviously, this website is still under construction: expect more content (and even more tweaking) in the coming weeks.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>